This means that we will realize that the eye, in fact, gives us a huge illusion.
For example, you feel like I exist here in front of you.
You truly have that feeling.
In fact, I am a mirage.
I will occasionally disappear like this.
So, and especially, thank you to Dominique for this invitation
to present this work.
So the idea here will also be,
well, you know a bit about all the health conditions,
I think everyone should be responsible for themselves,
knowing what to do and not do.
I invite you to, especially, in this context here,
to wash your hands, actually, frequently.
I think that's where a lot happens,
especially since we will touch the body a bit.
We won't undress, but we will still touch the body.
So the only thing I suggest to you,
is to be attentive, to wash your hands well.
And if you have any mild symptoms
or things like that, keep your mask on
but the most important thing
will still be hand washing
there's a study that was done
where the transmission was reduced by 98%
just through handwashing, in large contexts
so
that's my only proposal
and then I encourage you to be responsible
for each other.
What’s your name?
Anne-Marie.
We don’t know each other yet.
Anne-Marie, I think.
Some new people here, others I already know.
So hello everyone, I hope you all are doing well too.
So here we will see a few considerations actually,
which I hope will allow you, help you in your practice,
in your search.
In this search for osteopathy on a purely structural,
functional level, but also on a...
perhaps a bit more spiritual level.
I believe that osteopathy can lead us to a notion,
to an elevation of each person.
And I think, in particular, of an American named Joanna
Macy.
Joanna Macy, she wrote a book,
and just the title of this book, I didn’t even need to read it.
The title was enough to give me a sort of...
revelation, an awareness as well.
The book is called The Earth, the planet, as
oneself.
This means perhaps that we have a way of being ourselves,
a vision that we have, and in fact, we have a very limited view of ourselves.
And perhaps we could consider during these few days already,
and perhaps longer.
In any case, it’s something I’m starting to pay more and more attention to, it
is to consider the earth perhaps as myself, not in a sense, you see, but rather in a notion
of respect.
And then to consider the earth as a beloved, as my beloved,
you know.
Because, ultimately, I
am going to talk to you about what we call aggregates.
First of all, this term...
You might not know what it is, aggregates.
Ultimately, we are a sum of aggregates.
We are a composition, you see, momentary, impermanent, interdependent,
coming and going.
And within these aggregates, we speak, among other things, of form, and we speak, among other things, of earth, you
see.
And also of the great game of perceptions, because we're going to work a bit with that.
the great game of perceptions. And in this great game of perceptions, ultimately, after
observation,
our perceptions, if we observe them well, are only like
mirages. In fact, there is something
very blurry, ultimately. We think, because we have fixed things, but
ultimately, it's still
quite blurry. So, it’s this notion of interpretation, this notion of...
how we see things, how we perceive the things around us. And so the game that
has been built, ultimately, is also an interpretation,
an interpretation of
things, of phenomena. Ultimately, we are a phenomenology. So
the idea is
perhaps we could change this mode of perception a bit, maybe going
into
another mirage, perhaps a mirage a bit bigger, maybe as large as the
So I think it's interesting to say, hey, if we have this awareness that we
would be like this planet and that we become aware, you see, really, we would take
perhaps a bit more care of this planet, because we must also be aware that we
are indeed in the current context.
in the context in which society finds itself,
in this context of climate crisis,
which is still something extremely important.
I believe that we are not yet fully aware of it.
Yes, we are, but a bit like a mirage, ultimately.
In this context of social crisis,
which is also a significant event we are going through.
In this context...
also of all that will be immigration, which will be very important
in fact we are actually I
think at a really significant turning point and
we call this the great turning, you know, so we
are in a society, you know very well, where we operate in what we call the homunculus
economicus that is to say that we are in a society where we are
the growth. But in fact, we operate completely in this mode of growth.
We are completely caught up in it, in this industrial growth, in this
growth that ultimately considers the world as something infinite, while
we
are in a finite world. There is a real change. And if
I’m telling you about this, it’s
because I would like to propose, invite you to a view
a bit different.
Because we are heading towards this
that we either manage to make this turn or we
are going towards a collapse anyway.
It’s obvious given the fact that these are theories of emergence.
And these will be theories of emergence that are always seen in
as even in the body.
It emerges and then collapses.
And the society we are in, we are at...
this tipping point.
I think we, as therapists,
have a role, in fact,
to play. A role
to play of perhaps
guiding our patients
through this relief of
suffering we provide, but also through this notion
of opening up, you see.
Joanna Macy said, we will need
three things. Three things to
perhaps make this turn.
The very first thing,
is that somehow we need to mobilize a bit.
There have been movements like this that have occurred,
where we must say, no, it’s no.
But it’s no, not specifically, you see,
it’s also no, to oneself, you see, to be in this hyper-system.
It’s also, at some point, to say no.
No, that’s enough now, you see.
I must become aware.
The second thing that is important,
is to create new ideas, new forms.
As I think we will see well, at
the end,
that this climate crisis relocates things.
Rahman has a new awareness, a new view.
That’s also the view I want to propose to you.
It’s to be aware of this, this new view.
This notion, it’s...
but it leads us to be creators, to be
thinkers.
And that brings us to a third thing that is very important.
It’s that we also, for me to speak of three things, you remember,
the first thing was to mobilize a little, but to mobilize oneself too.
The second thing is to find other solutions, think about other possibilities,
other views.
And the third thing is to do spiritual work.
I think if these three conditions, at least, this is what Joanna
Macy proposes,
if these three conditions are not met, we will not be able to make this turn.
We will be limited.
And this spiritual work, ultimately, is a work
that we do here.
It’s also a form of spiritual work that we will do.
That is to say developing beautiful awareness, good heart,
that this is not a course on religion, but it is still a course on a
consciousness.
I think at this spiritual level, we are in this elevation.
That is, we must ask ourselves how we can reduce the
suffering as well.
But not just my own.
Not just yours, but perhaps open up a bit, because I
think of Cominada.
You know Cominada, he’s one of the leaders of Greenpeace.
He said, I think you, therapists, you, meditators,
you have the ability, without realizing it, to
teach others.
another form of pleasure.
Because we are constantly searching for pleasure, in fact,
desire, pleasure.
Perhaps we have the capacity,
through our work,
to teach others
the discovery of another form of pleasure.
So, for example,
because most of the time,
we are just enjoying our senses.
I was surprised the other day I was in the city and
I was walking around and I saw that all
my system was being drawn to please me I
went into a bookstore and I was looking
and then at one point I said but what I really need is this I already have 30,000
books not even the time but in fact I still needed and so
I said to myself, hey, and then I started to observe, and so it’s this notion that
I will propose to you, it’s to learn here, it’s to learn to observe yourself,
to learn to observe your behaviors, in the view of these behaviors.
So, these three things are important, this spiritual notion is fundamental.
This spiritual notion, it’s in that sense that we must, we have this role
to learn
to teach others.
perhaps another form of pleasure than just our sensory pleasures.
I think that’s part of this turning point.
So consider this for a few days, if you have the opportunity,
that you are as great as the Earth.
But would you throw
papers?
Well, you see, things are getting better now, but we all have behaviors, all states.
you will see that if you consider this
you will begin to have a sort of
whoops, hey
I will consider myself
so we will enlarge your game
so I will give you a huge ego
you will be as big as the Earth
for a few days and maybe longer
after all, the Earth is not bad
it’s fine that we are leaving now
so that’s a little bit
the idea too is that
it’s a little bit
This is also part of this transition, you see, so that we can find pleasure,
but elsewhere, in fact, daring to abandon some of our pleasures,
you see, by perhaps replacing them with something else, like
discovering the pleasure of simplicity.
Have you ever experienced this, a pleasure of simplicity?
The pleasure of a...
True presence.
The pleasure that can come from the relationship
to things
rather than the possession of things.
The pleasure of the relationship to things
rather than the pleasure of possession.
Because we think we possess something, no.
In fact, we do not possess.
The pleasure of contentment.
It’s the little things that come from a certain neutrality.
So, the joy of renunciation.
At the beginning, when you read texts like that, Buddhist texts, you see, Buddha said, at first,
my heart was angry to have to renounce.
And then now that I have
experienced it, I leap for joy in this release. My heart leaps with joy
to be able to renounce
certain things. So, I propose to you
to reflect like this. What could you
abandon that actually adds suffering to you? There are things like
that in my behavior. What can I abandon that adds suffering to me?
that add suffering to my life, or even to others.
And so I think that, I tell you, as a therapist,
we may also have this role, in a way, to open this
awareness
that we will have to shift a bit towards this level,
and perhaps find a bit of simplicity.
I am someone who meditates a lot and often does very simple retreats, very
simple retreats.
And so I sometimes discover, from time to time, my mind, naturally,
wanders a lot, but at the same time, I have sometimes discovered this
pleasure of this simplicity,
to be simply present to my breath, to be simply present to small things like that which are
there.
This means that at a certain point
you will almost have a joy
of losing
certain privileges of yours
if it becomes a joy, that would be good
that was a little bit
the view, the introduction
I wrote this yesterday
it was a little bit
the idea
that we can expand our view a bit
that we can change a little bit
it’s a little bit
the work
in which we will be involved
it’s a new view
a new vision perhaps of things
it’s now